Chris: We have looked at the various
risks that may affect a project,
but what can you do to reduce risks
and carry out risk mitigation?
It’s worth considering that when a
project is still at a very early stage
there will many unknowns and some may
even impact getting the project started.
So how can you ensure that
risks are reduced or mitigated?
Let’s look at what steps you can take.
• Leah: Identify potential risks
• Evaluate the risks
identified and prioritise
• Plan how the risks that have
been identified can be managed or
mitigated using Agile methodology
• Undertake regular reviews to evaluate
if the identified risks are likely to
occur and if so, implement appropriate
actions to mitigate the impact.
• Monitor for any new risks that may arise
• Provide updates to stakeholders on
the status of existing risks and any
new risks that may potentially arise.
Chris: Let’s now look at how some of
the most common risks can be mitigated.
Missing or unclear requirements
A failure to capture and fully understand
all the requirements of the project
is a poor foundation for success.
Ideally everyone involved will
be clear on exactly what the
requirements are, and this reinforces
the importance of planning.
However, if requirements are missing
or unclear, using Agile methodology
can help in mitigating risks.
By going for an iterative development
cycle and meeting with customers/clients
at every stage of the development
process on completion of each iteration,
team members can show stakeholders
the progress made and review the
results so ensuring relevancy.
Leah: Skills shortage
Skilled software developers are always
in demand and if people leave mid
project, it can directly impact the Agile
methodology being used, especially if it
is the ‘project owner’ or ‘scrum master’.
As the team will be working in ‘sprints’,
the amount of work to be completed in the
‘sprint timeframe’ will have been agreed,
and the loss of one or more individuals
may result in failure of the ‘sprint goal’
impacting the timeframe of the project.
It may also be that the project requires
new skills to be learnt which will
have an impact but identifying this
early in the planning process can
help resolve this in a timely manner.
Looking at the skillsets of others within
the organisation can help identify where
that skills shortage can be filled.
A flexible and multiskilled workforce
offers the opportunity to draw on other
teams or individuals if and when required.
Chris: Time delays
Running out of time is always a
constant threat on any project.
This is far more damaging in certain
methodologies such as ‘Waterfall’
or ‘Kanban’ which follow a linear
approach, where one stage has to be
completed before the next begins.
By using an ‘Agile methodology’
such as ‘scrum’ several stages are
being worked on at the same time,
so delays to one task will not
impact the completion of the others.
Leah: Over budget
A project may run over budget for
several reasons like issues within
the development team or perhaps more
likely to do with client requirements.
Clients may change the requirement
mid project or there may be new
technological reasons why changes
have to be made or new features added.
Working in Agile such as scrum, can
mitigate this as it gives the opportunity
to take a look at the projects scope
and see if there is any opportunity to
reduce this, but still meet requirements.
This can give a deliverable product
meeting requirements in the short term
that can be developed into versioning,
so changes may be made in later releases.
Chris: Resource shortages
Resource shortages especially human
resources can be a major risk.
Resources may often be
being used by other teams.
When planning, working out the resources
required can be difficult, but forecasting
possible resource risks is important.
Creating a ‘resource allocation plan’
and analysing it to see potential
risks and disruptions, can enable the
project manager to build in mitigation.
Some critical tasks may need to be
completed by one specific individual,
what if they are unavailable?
To mitigate any impact, other
team members can be upskilled
to ensure risk is minimised.
‘Capacity planning’ is a way to
ensure that the organisation has
sufficient resources for your project,
identifying what resources are available
compared to demand, and if required,
increasing or re-allocating them.
Leah: Decision making
Although it may be assumed the project
manager is the one making the decisions,
when working in an Agile environment
such as Scrum, the team members are
also responsible for making decisions.
Part of creating a well-functioning
team involves giving members the
autonomy needed for the project.
Scrum pushes the level of decision
making downward, team members need
to feel they have the autonomy, to
become truly invested in the project.
Using Jira boards or project boards
in GitHub can help show any potential
bottlenecks or issues arising, which
makes decision making easier, as
these issues will need to be resolved.